原视频名：How Did The Apollo 11 Documentary Get Film Of The Upper Stage Ignition
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/780SAiciNbU
原视频发布日期：20190325
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello, its Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Many of you have gone to see the Apollo 11 documentary
你们中的许多人都去看了阿波罗11号的纪录片
and man if you have agreed with my assessment that it is very much worth seeing
兄啊 如果你同意我的评价 认为这是非常值得看的话 (那就很好)
but also some of you have had some questions
但也有一些人有一些问题
and there's one particular question which I did not know the answer to it.
而且有一个特别的问题 我之前并不知道它的答案
And I was equally perplexed when I saw the footage.
而当我看到这段录像时 也同样感到困惑
So what did it this shows is the lighting of the third stage of the Saturn V.
那么它这显示的是土星五号三级的点火
That is the S-IVB upper stage
那就是S-IVB上面级
which is a hundred-plus ton hydrogen oxygen stage propelled by a single J-2 engine.
这是一个一百多吨的氢氧级 由一台J-2发动机推动
This gets the spacecraft into its initial parking orbit
这使航天器进入最初的停泊轨道
and then after a couple of orbits they relit it
然后在几圈轨道后 他们再重新点燃它
and that would carry the spacecraft all the way up into translunar injection.
这将携带航天器一路上升到月球转移轨道
It was a very short clip and I thought it might have been shot from the ground
这是一个非常短的片段 我想它可能是从地面上拍摄的
but that wouldn't have been possible with Apollo 11
但如果是阿波罗11号 就不可能了
because the engine was relit in the dark side of the earth and so we wouldn't have seen that
因为发动机是在地球黑暗的一面重新点燃的 所以我们看不到的(至少看不到箭体)
but the movie had been quite happy borrowing some footage from other missions.
但电影却很乐意借用其他任务的一些镜头
Most notably this stage separations were from engineering cameras which were not carried on Apollo 11.
最值得注意的是这个分级是来自工程摄像机 而这些摄像机并没有在阿波罗11号上携带
In fact this very famous shot isn't even from a Saturn V. It is from a Saturn IB.
事实上 这个非常著名的镜头甚至不是来自土星五号 而是来自土星一B
You can tell because the interstage isn't tapered
你可以看出来 因为级间段并不是锥形的
and because it has three stage separation Rockets before the main J-2 engine lights up.
同时因为它在J-2主发动机点火前有三个分离火箭
The Saturn V version used a different configuration
土星五号的版本采用了不同的配置
because they needed to be able to relight the engine later.
因为发动机需要在之后再进行点火
Anyway it's kind of cool that these images they come from a film camera that was located inside there
不管怎么说 这些图像是很酷的 它们来自于一台就放置在那个位置的胶片相机
and it was designed to be ejected and recovered later.
而且它被设计成可以被弹射出去 然后再回收
If you skip to the end of this segment
如果你跳到这段的最后
then you get to see the camera starting to leave the interstage just as it's film runs out
你就会看到摄像机在它的胶片用完的时候 开始离开级间段
so the cameras would then parachute back into the ocean and be recovered
这样 在这之后相机就会使用降落伞落到海里 然后再被回收
although I believe in one case they parachuted into the middle of a storm
虽然我认为 在某次中 相机被降落到了风暴的中间
and it would be something like a month before they were recovered afterwards.
而在一个月后才回收
But coming back to the footage of that upper stage relighting.
但回到那个上面级再次点火的镜头
It turns out that this is from Apollo 9.
原来 这是阿波罗9号的画面
So Apollo 9 was gonna be the first major test of the lunar module.
阿波罗9号将是登月舱的第一次重大测试
It was gonna fly around in low earth orbit
它将在近地轨道上飞行
and for that they needed to have the full Saturn V to launch the payload into orbit
为此 他们需要加注土星五号来将有效载荷送入轨道
so after they got into low earth orbit
所以在他们进入近地轨道后
the crew did the regular transposition docking and extraction of the lunar module for testing.
乘员们进行了常规的换位对接和登月舱的提取测试
This would actually be the only time this manoeuvre was performed in low earth orbit
这实际上是唯一一次在近地轨道上进行这个机动动作
because at all the other missions
因为在所有其他任务中
this would be done after they had performed the translunar injection and were already on their way to the moon.
这都会发生在他们完成了进入月球转移轨道的机动之后 并且处在前往月球的路上
Because they hadn't made that burn to send them on a course towards the moon
因为他们还没有进行那次把他们送到月球转移轨道上的点火
the upper stage still had a lot of propellant left inside it
上面级还残留着大量的推进剂
and of course they're gonna be doing all sorts of experimental operations in the command module and the lunar module
当然 在指令舱和登月舱中 他们会做各种实验性的操作
so it's not a good idea
所以这不是一个好主意
to have 50 tons of fuel and oxidizer sitting around in well somewhere that could just explode.
也就是呆在可能会爆炸的50吨的燃料和氧化剂周围
So the decision or the design of the mission was that they would relight the engine to test it
所以这次任务的决定或设计是 他们会重新点燃发动机来测试它的性能
and send it off further away from the spacecraft
并让其远离航天器
so that they can actually test in peace
以便他们能够真正安全地进行测试
without worrying about something that might say explode if they looked at the wrong way
而不用担心如果搞错了就会爆炸的东西
and so the crew of Apollo 9 were able to document this both in photographs and in a film
所以阿波罗9号的乘员能够用照片和影片的形式来记录这一切
showing the engine relighting and sending the spacecraft off into a distant orbit.
录像中显示发动机再次点火 并将航天器送入遥远的轨道
It's also worth noting that
值得注意的是
that footage was taken when the spacecraft was pretty much sitting behind the engine
这段录像是在 当航天器几乎是放在发动机后面的时候拍摄的
and you may think that sounds pretty scary
你可能觉得这听起来很可怕
because you got a rocket engine facing towards you
因为这火箭发动机正对着你
but there was something like five hundred to a thousand feet away
但其实这差不多是在152米到304米之外的地方
and that was way safer than being in front of it or to the sides of it
那比在前面或两边都要安全得多
say if it were to explode that would be the most likely place debris would go.
(因为)如果它爆炸的话 碎片最可能会飞到那些地方去
Anyway while the crew were readying themselves the next part of the mission
总之 当乘员们在准备进行下一步的任务时
the upper stage would actually perform a second burn later in this orbit
实际上 上面级将在这一轨道上进行第二次点火
which would take it up to escape velocity and into heliocentric orbit.
这将使它达到逃逸速度并进入日心轨道
They actually had a problem with the engine possibly and it was not really clear
实际上 他们的发动机可能有问题 但并不十分清楚
but the thrust dropped and the spacecraft did actually complete its entire burn.
但推力下降 同时航天器确实完成了整个点火过程
This would have been critical if it happens during a crewed mission to the moon
如果这种情况发生在载人登月任务中 那将是问题严重的
but in this case the spacecraft or the upper stage was just heading off beyond Earth's sphere of influence
但在这种情况下 航天器或者说上面级只是飞向了地球(引力)的影响范围之外
and it's in a heliocentric orbit as of today.
到今天为止 它已经在日心轨道上了
Apollo 9 would also be the first proper test of the Apollo spacesuit with the onboard life support.
阿波罗9号也将是阿波罗宇航服与机载生命支持系统的第一次真正的测试
Previously every spacewalk in had been done used an umbilical connected to the spacecraft's life-support
此前每一次太空行走都是用一根脐带连接到飞船的生命支持系统上的
but this was the first one with a backpack that was all self-contained
但这是第一次使用独立背包的
and it would be the first time they tested it really before going to the moon
而且这将是他们在登月前第一次真正的测试
One of the astronauts performing this EVA is Rusty Schweickart
这次执行EVA的宇航员之一是Rusty Schweickart
who is one of the founders of the B612 foundation of course I'm a big fan of.
他是B612基金会的创始人之一 当然我是他的忠实粉丝
As it would turn out this would be his only spaceflight.
事实证明 这将是他唯一的一次太空飞行
He was also the pilot of the lunar module here
他也是这次登月舱的飞行员
and on that they would take it out
所以他们会把登月舱开出去
and they pretty much went for a joyride traveling out 100 miles away from the command module
他们几乎是去兜风了 飞到了距离指令舱有161公里的地方
before coming back and demonstrating that the spacecraft was controllable.
之后才飞回来 证明飞船是可控的
Anyway yeah I wanted to talk a bit more about the S-IVB upper stage
总之 是的 我想多谈一点关于S-IVB上面级的事情
that was the designation for the upper stage of the Saturn V and for the Saturn IB.
这是土星五号和土星一B的上面级的名称
The original S-IV was actually a slightly different design that was used on the Saturn I launches
最初的S-IV实际上是一个稍有不同的设计 用于土星一号的发射
It had instead of a single J-2 engine, it had a cluster of six RL-10 engines.
它的发动机不是一台J-2 而是由6台RL-10发动机组成的一组发动机
The reason for this cluster of engines was
之所以采用这组发动机 是因为
because the Saturn I was kinda developed very early
土星一号是很早就开发出来了
before the JFK gave his whole let's go to the moon speech.
早于肯尼迪的那个登月演讲
It was built out of the stuff they had laying around.
它是用他们闲置的东西建造的
The main tank instead of developing a new bigger tank
主储罐不是从头研发的新的大储罐
they took 8 Redstone missile tanks and strung those around the outside
而是拿了8个红石导弹的储罐 然后把它们串在外面
and then they had another tank in the middle.
然后再在中间加另外一个储罐
They had eight h1 Rockets.
他们有八个H1火箭发动机
And then the upper stage of course as I said they have six RL-10 engines on it.
然后上面级当然就像我说的那样 有六个RL-10发动机加在上面
This was what they could find to make a big heavy lift rocket
这就是他们能找到的制造大的重型运载火箭的方法
and it was used early on in the Apollo program to basically test stuff.
基本上 它在阿波罗计划的早期被用来测试东西
But by the time they were ready to put people on top of this
但当他们准备把人放在这个上面的时候
it had evolved into their Saturn IB and the upper stage was of course this S-IVB.
它已经演变成了土星一B 而上面级当然是这个S-IVB
It was would be practically the same upper stage that was used on the Saturn V.
它的上面级几乎和土星五号上使用的一样
So look while it wasn't as sexy as the space capsules of the lunar landers
所以你看 虽然它没有登月舱那么好看
it did launch more as part of the Apollo program and it was a critical part.
但作为阿波罗计划的一部分 它确实发射了更多的东西 而且是一个关键的部分
The guidance for the entire Saturn V was in the top of this stage.
整个土星五号的制导装置就在这一级的顶部
When Apollo 12 was hit by lightning and the command module lost all its instrumentation
当阿波罗12号被闪电击中时 指令舱失去了所有的仪器设备(的控制)
IMU = Inertial measurement unit，惯性测量单元
the IMU on the upper stage kept running.
而上面级的IMU一直在运行
SCE = Signal Conditioning Equipment, AUX = Auxiliary
It kept the mission under control until the crew could find the SCE and switch it to AUX.
这让任务处于控制之下 直到乘员们能找到SCE并将其切换到AUX上
So I think it's kind of cool there are some of these things still floating around in deep space.
所以我觉得这些东西还漂浮在深空是件很酷的事
You know like monuments to the Apollo program.
就像阿波罗计划的纪念碑一样
It wasn't just Apollo 9's upper stage that could boost it into a heliocentric orbit.
不仅仅是阿波罗9号的上面级会被推到了日心轨道上
it was all from Apollo 8 through 12 that were boosted out this way and missed the moon.
从阿波罗8号到12号都是这样被推动而错过了月球
But they're not all lost in the depths of space.
但它们并不是都消失在太空深处
In 2002 astronomer Bill Young found what looked like an asteroid orbiting the earth.
在2002年 天文学家Bill Young发现了一个看起来像绕着地球运行的小行星一样的东西
When a spectroscopy was applied to it
当光谱仪对着它进行探测时
the colors were consistent with the white titanium dioxide paint that was used on those upper stages.
颜色与那些上面级所使用的白色二氧化钛涂料一致
So it was look they trace the orbit back and they discovered that back in 1971,
所以他们追踪了过去的轨道数据 并发现早在1971年
it had been kicked out of its a loosely bound orbit into deep space.
上面级被踢出了松散的被地球引力束缚的轨道 进入了深空
And then spent about 31 years orbiting the Sun
然后花了大约31年的时间绕着太阳转了一圈
before it returned close enough to the earth
之后才足够靠近地球
and had an interaction with the moon
并与月球相互影响
allowed the spacecraft or the debris to be captured in a bound orbit for a few years.
使航天器或者说残骸能够在一个约束轨道上被捕获几年
In 2003 it was kicked back off into deep space again and it may return in about 2040 or there abouts.
在2003年 它又被踢回深空 可能在2040年左右返回
Most people believe this was from Apollo 12
大多数人认为这是来自阿波罗12号的
which is coincidentally the last time a stage ended up going into deep space.
巧合的是 这也是最后一次有上面级进入深空
From Apollo 13 onwards they started crashing them into the moon to collect more science.
从阿波罗13号开始 他们让上面级坠入月球 以收集更多的科学数据
Most of the Apollo missions included surface science packages which had seismometers on them.
大多数阿波罗任务都包含了带有月震仪的月表科学包
The one on Apollo 11 failed after 21 days but the one on Apollo 12 it kept going
阿波罗11号上的月震仪在21天后失效了 但阿波罗12号上的月震仪却一直在运行着
and bso from Apollo 13 onward they were smashing those stages into the moon
所以从阿波罗13号开始 他们就把那些上面级砸到月球上了
to make seismic waves that would enable them to collect more data about the the lunar interior.
制造月震波 使他们能够收集更多关于月球内部的数据
Also these serve really nice examples to
还有这些(人造陨石坑)是非常好的例子
people they like to tell me that craters on the moon aren't created when things hit the moon at very high speeds.
对于那些喜欢跟我说这种言论的人 比如月球上的陨石坑并不是高速物体撞击月球产生的
There is one case of an S-IVB which didn't make it to space before getting destroyed.
有一个S-IVB的案例 它在被摧毁之前没有进入太空
It decided to blow up on the test stand
它决定 在试验台上爆炸
which was well rather dramatic unfortunately we didn't have any good camera recordings of it.
遗憾的是 我们没有任何好的摄像机将这个画面记录下来
But perhaps the most storied S-IVB upper stage was the last one launched on a Saturn V.
但也许最传奇的S-IVB上面级是在最后一个土星五号上发射的
It has undergone a bit of conversion.
它经过了一番改装
Instead of carrying a large hydrogen tank and an oxygen tank,
并没有携带一个大型的氢气罐和一个氧气罐
they had cleared out all that space and decided to put crew quarters, a shower, solar panels.
而是已经腾出了所有的空间 并决定放入一个乘员居住区 一个浴室 一些太阳能电池板
They had turned it into Skylab.
他们把它变成了天空实验室
So you can see what was the hydrogen tank became the main accommodation area.
所以 你可以看到氢气罐所在的地方 成为乘员的主要生活区
The oxygen tank was actually used for storing garbage.
而氧气罐实际上是用来存储垃圾的
The Skylab never really dumped any of its garbage during its time.
(但)天空实验室在它服役的时期内 从来没有真正地倾倒任何垃圾
In fact it still had a bunch of supplies left when it was finished.
事实上 当它完成服役的时候 它还剩下了一堆物资
Because it was so much larger than the International Space Station
因为它的体积比国际空间站大得多
you're able to see these crazy acrobatics that are just not possible in the space station these days
你能看到这些疯狂的杂技动作 这在现在的空间站里是不可能实现的
because it had to fit into a much smaller area.
因为动作必须适应在一个更小的区域内
But of course Skylab's life turned out to be a bit more limited than originally planned.
但当然 最终天空实验室的寿命比原来计划的还要少一些
The space shuttle was never developed in time to enable it to be reboosted.
(因为)航天飞机并没有及时地开发出来 使之轨道得到再次提升
And eventually it fell back to earth scattering debris over the Australian outback.
最终它落回了地球 在澳大利亚的内陆地区散落着碎片
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]